<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "custom-docbook.dtd">
<chapter id="cpp-dev">
  <title>&Cpp; Development</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      The &Omnetpp; IDE contains editors, views and other tools to assist you while developing
      your &Cpp; code. &Cpp; files open in the IDE in the &Cpp; source editor. The &Cpp; source editor supports syntax
      highlighting, documentation tooltips, content assist, automatic indentation, code formatting,
      refactoring, and several other useful features. The IDE also allows you to configure the build,
      start the build process, launch simulations, and debug the model without leaving the IDE.
    </para>
    <para>
      Most of these features are provided by the Eclipse CDT (C/&Cpp; Development Tooling)
      project (http://eclipse.org/cdt). This chapter briefly explains the basics of using CDT for
      developing simulation models. If you want to learn more about how to use CDT effectively, we
      recommend that you read the CDT documentation in the IDE help system (Help/Help Content).
    </para>

    <para>
      The &Omnetpp; IDE extends CDT with the following features to make model development easier:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          A new &Omnetpp; project creation wizard allows you to create simple, working
          simulation models in one step.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Makefiles are automatically generated for your project based on the project build configuration.
          The built-in makefile generator is compatible with the command line [[opp_makemake]] tool,
          and features deep makefiles, recursive make, cross-project references, invoking the message compiler,
          automatic linking with the &Omnetpp; libraries; and can build executables, shared libraries or
          static libraries.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Makefile generation and the project build system can be configured using a GUI interface.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            Project Features: Large projects can be partitioned into smaller units which can be
            independently excluded or included in the build. Disabling parts of the project
            can significantly reduce build time or make it possible to build the project at all.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <para>
      The &Omnetpp; IDE (and the &Omnetpp; simulation framework itself) requires a
      preinstalled compiler toolchain to function properly.
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          On Windows: The &Omnetpp;  distribution comes with a preconfigured MinGW compiler toolchain,
          there is no need to manually install anything. By default, the IDE uses the Clang compiler
          from MinGW, but it is also possible to switch to the GCC compiler (also part of MinGW).
          <commercial>&Omnetpp; can also use the Clang/C2 compiler from your Microsoft Visual Studio installation.</commercial>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          On Linux: By default, the Clang compiler is used, but &Omnetpp; falls back to use GCC
          if Clang is not present on the system. You have to install Clang or GCC
          on your system before trying to compile a simulation with &Omnetpp;. Please read the
          Install Guide for detailed instructions.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          On macOS: You need to install Xcode Developer Tools to get compiler
          support before trying to compile a simulation with &Omnetpp;.
          Please read the Install Guide for detailed instructions.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Creating a &Cpp; Project</title>
    <para>
      To create an &Omnetpp; project that supports &Cpp; development, select
      ``File | New | &Omnetpp; Project''.
    </para>
    <picture file="pictures/Intro-NewProject.png">Creating an &Omnetpp; project</picture>
    <para>
      This menu item will bring up the ``New &Omnetpp; Project'' wizard.
      The wizard lets you create an &Omnetpp;-specific project, which includes support
      for NED, MSG and INI file editing, as well as &Cpp; development of simple modules.
    </para>
    <para> On the first page of the wizard, specify the project name and ensure that the ``Support
      &Cpp; Development'' checkbox is selected.</para>
    <picture file="pictures/CPP-NewProjectWizard.png"> Setting project name and enabling &Cpp; support</picture>
    <para> Select a project template. A template defines the initial content and layout of the
        project. </para>
    <picture file="pictures/CPP-NewProjectWizard1.png">Selecting a project template</picture>
    <para>Select a toolchain that is supported on your platform. Usually you will see only a single
      supported toolchain, so there is no need to change anything on the page.</para>
    <picture file="pictures/CPP-NewProjectWizard2.png">Selecting a toolchain</picture>
    <para>Finally, select one or more from the preset build configurations. A configuration is a set of
        options that are associated with the build process. It is used mainly to build debug and release
        versions of your program.
    </para>
    <picture file="pictures/CPP-NewProjectWizard3.png">Selecting configurations</picture>
    <para>
         Pressing the ``Finish'' button will create the project.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Editing &Cpp; Code</title>
    <para>
      The &Omnetpp;
      IDE comes with a C/&Cpp; editor. In addition to standard editing features, the C/&Cpp; editor
      provides syntax highlighting, content assistance, and other &Cpp; specific functionality.
      The source is continually parsed as you type, and errors and warnings are displayed as
      markers on the editor rulers.
    </para>
    <picture file="pictures/CPP-Editor.png">&Cpp; source editor</picture>

    <sect2>
      <title>The &Cpp; Editor</title>

      <para> The &Cpp; source editor provides the usual features of Eclipse-based text editors,
        such as syntax highlighting, clipboard cut/copy/paste, unlimited undo/redo, folding,
        find/replace and incremental search.
      </para>

      <para> The IDE scans and indexes the &Cpp; files in your project in the background, and provides
        navigation and code analysis features on top of that knowledge; this database
        is kept up to date as you edit the source.
      </para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Basic Functions</title>
        <para>Some of the most useful features of the source editor:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Undo (<keycap>Ctrl+Z</keycap>), Redo (<keycap>Ctrl+Y</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Switch between a &Cpp; source and its matching header file (<keycap>Ctrl+TAB</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Indent/unindent code blocks (<keycap>TAB/Shift+TAB</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Correct indentation (<keycap>Ctrl+I</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Move lines (<keycap>Alt+UP/DOWN</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Find (<keycap>Ctrl+F</keycap>), incremental search (<keycap>Ctrl+J</keycap>)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <tip>
            <para>The following functions can help you explore the IDE:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para><keycap>Ctrl+Shift+L</keycap> pops up a window that lists all keyboard bindings, and </para></listitem>
              <listitem><para><keycap>Ctrl+3</keycap> brings up a filtered list of all available commands.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </tip>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>View Documentation</title>
        <para>
          Hovering the mouse over an identifier will display its declaration and the documentation comment
          in a "tooltip" window. The window can be made persistent by hitting <keycap>F2</keycap>.
        </para>
        <tip>
            <para>If you are on Ubuntu and you see all-black tooltips, you need to change the tooltip colors
            in Ubuntu; see the Ubuntu chapter of the ``&Omnetpp; Installation Guide'' for details.</para>
        </tip>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Content Assist</title>
        <para>
          If you need help, just press <keycap>Ctrl+SPACE</keycap>.
          The editor will offer possible completions (variable names, type names, argument lists, etc.).
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Navigation</title>
        <para>
          Hitting <keycap>F3</keycap> or holding the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
          key and clicking an identifier will jump to the definition/declaration.
        </para>
        <para>The Eclipse platform's bookmarking and navigation history facilities are also available in the &Cpp; editor.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Commenting</title>
        <para>
          To comment out the selected lines, press <keycap>Ctrl+/</keycap>.
          To remove the comment, press <keycap>Ctrl+/</keycap> again.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Open Type</title>
        <para>
            Pressing <keycap>Ctrl+Shift+T</keycap> will bring up the ``Open Element'' dialog which lets
            you type a class name, method name or other identifier, and opens its declaration in a new editor.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Exploring the Code</title>
        <para>The editor offers various ways to explore the code:
            Open Declaration (<keycap>F3</keycap>), Open Type Hierarchy (<keycap>F4</keycap>),
            Open Call Hierarchy (<keycap>Ctrl+Alt+H</keycap>),
            Quick Outline (<keycap>Ctrl+O</keycap>), Quick Type Hierarchy (<keycap>Ctrl+T</keycap>),
            Explore Macro Expansion (<keycap>Ctrl+=</keycap>),
            Search for References (<keycap>Ctrl+Shift+G</keycap>), etc.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Refactoring</title>
        <para>
            Several refactoring operations are available, for example Rename (<keycap>Shift+Alt+R</keycap>).
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <note>
          Several features such as content assist, go to definition, type hierarchy and refactorings
          rely on the ``Index''. The index contains the locations of all functions, classes, enums,
          defines, etc. in the project and referenced projects. Initial indexing of large projects
          may take a significant amount of time. The index is kept up to date mostly automatically,
          but occasionally it may be necessary to manually request reindexing the project.
          Index-related actions can be found in the ``Index'' submenu of the project's context menu.
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
        <title>Include Browser View</title>
        <para>Dropping a &Cpp; file into the ``Include Browser View'' displays the include files used by the
        &Cpp; file (either directly or indirectly).</para>
        <picture file="pictures/CPP-IncludeBrowserView.png">Include Browser</picture>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
        <title>Outline View</title>
        <para>During source editing, the ``Outline View'' gives you an overview of the structure of your source
        file and can be used to quickly navigate inside the file.</para>
        <picture file="pictures/CPP-OutlineView.png">Navigating with Outline View</picture>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
        <title>Type Hierarchy View</title>
        <para>Displaying the &Cpp; type hierarchy may be helpful for understanding
        the inheritance relationships among your classes (and among &Omnetpp; classes).
        </para>
        <picture file="pictures/CPP-TypeHierarchy.png">&Cpp; Type hierarchy</picture>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Building the Project</title>
    <sect2>
        <title>Basics</title>
        <para>Once you have created your source files and configured your project settings, you can build the
        project by selecting ``Build Project'' from the ``Project'' menu or from the project context menu.
        You can also press <keycap>Ctrl+B</keycap> to build all open projects in the workspace.
        <picture file="pictures/CPP-BuildProject.png">Building a project</picture>
        </para>

        <sect3>
          <title>Build Output</title>
          <para>The build output (standard output and standard error) is displayed in the ``Console View''
              as the build progresses. Errors and warnings parsed from the output are displayed in the
              ``Problems View''. Double-clicking a line in the ``Problems View'' will jump to the corresponding
              source line. Conversely, the ``Console View'' is more useful when you want to look
              at the build messages in their natural order (``Problems View'' is usually sorted),
              for example when you get a lot of build errors and you want to begin by looking at
              the first one.
          </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Makefile Generation</title>
          <para>When you start the build process, a makefile will be created or refreshed in each
             folder where makefile creation is configured. After that, make will be invoked with the [[all]]
             target in the folder configured as build root.
          </para>
        </sect3>
	<note>
	  During the build process, the makefile will print out only the names of the compiled files.
	  If you want to see the full command line used to compile each file, specify
	  [[V=1]] (verbose on) on the make command line. To add this option,
	  open ``Project Properties | C/&Cpp; Build | Behavior (tab)'' and replace [[all]] with [[all V=1]]
	  on the ``Build'' target line.
	</note>

        <sect3>
          <title>Cleaning the Project</title>
          <para>To clean the project, choose ``Clean...'' from the ``Project'' menu, or ``Clean Project'' from the
             project context menu. This will invoke [[make]] with the [[clean]] target in the project's
             build root folder, and also in referenced projects. To only clean the local project and keep
             referenced projects intact, use ``Clean Local'' item from the project context menu (see next section).
          </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Referenced Projects and the Build Process</title>
          <para>When you start the build, the IDE will build the referenced projects first. When you clean
              the project, the IDE will also clean the referenced projects first. This is often inconvenient
              (especially if your project depends on a large third party project). To avoid cleaning the
              referenced projects, use ``Clean Local'' from the project context menu.
          </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Build Configurations</title>
          <para>
              A project is built using the active build configuration. A project may have several build
              configurations, where each configuration selects a compiler toolchain, debug or release mode,
              defines symbols, etc. To set the active build configuration, choose ``Build Configurations | Set Active''
              from the project context menu.
              <picture file="pictures/CPP-BuildConfiguration.png">Activating a build configuration</picture>
          </para>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
        <title>Console View</title>
        <para>The ``Console View'' displays the output of the build process.</para>
        <picture file="pictures/CPP-ConsoleView.png">Build output in a console</picture>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
        <title>Problems View</title>
        <para>The ``Problems View'' contains the errors and warnings generated by the build process. You can
        browse the problem list and double-click any message to go to the problem location in the source file.
        NED file and INI file problems are also reported in this view along with &Cpp; problems. The editors
        are annotated with these markers, too. Hover over an error marker in the editor window to get the
        corresponding message as a tooltip.</para>
        <picture file="pictures/CPP-ProblemsView.png">&Cpp; problems</picture>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Configuring the Project</title>

    <sect2>
        <title>Configuring the Build Process</title>
        <para>The make invocation can be configured on ``C/&Cpp; Build'' page of the ``Project Properties'' dialog.
        Most settings are already set correctly and do not need to be changed. One exception is the
        ``Enable parallel build'' option on the ``Behavior'' tab that you may want to enable, especially
        if you have a multi-core computer.</para>

        <warning>
        Do not set the number of parallel jobs to be significantly higher than the number of CPU cores
        you have. In particular, never turn on the ``Use unlimited jobs'' option, as it will start
        an excessive number of compile processes, and can easy consume all available memory in the system.
        </warning>

        <para>We do not recommend that you change any setting on property pages under the
        ``C/&Cpp; Build'' tree node.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
        <title>Managing Build Configurations</title>
        <para>A project may have several build configurations, where each configuration describes
            the selected compiler toolchain, debug or release mode, any potential extra include and
            linker paths, defined symbols, etc. You can activate, create or delete build configurations
            under the ``Build Configurations'' submenu of the project context menu.
        </para>
        <note>
            Make sure that the names of all configurations contain the ``"debug"'' or the ``"release"'' substring.
            The IDE launcher uses the name of the configuration to switch the matching configuration
            depending whether you want to debug or run the simulation.
        </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
        <title>Configuring the Project Build System</title>
        <para>&Omnetpp; uses makefiles to build the project. You can use a single makefile for
        the whole project, or a hiearchy of makefiles. Each makefile may be hand-written
        (i.e. provided by you), or generated automatically. The IDE provides several
        options for automatically created makefiles.
        </para>
        <para>The build system for an &Omnetpp; project can be configured on the
        ``&Omnetpp; | Makemake'' page of the ``Project Properties'' dialog.
        All settings you do in this page will affect all build configurations.
        <picture file="pictures/CPP-SourceFolder.png">Configuring Makefiles</picture>
        </para>

        <sect3><title>Folders and Makefiles</title>
            <para>The page displays the folder tree of the project. Using controls on
            the page (``Build'' group in the top-right corner), you can declare that
            a selected folder contains a hand-written (custom) makefile, or
            tell the IDE to generate a makefile for you. Generated makefiles will be
            automatically refreshed before each build.  If a makefile is configured
            for a folder, the makefile kind will be indicated with a small
            decoration on the folder icon.
            </para>

            <para>The build root folder is indicated with a small arrow. This is the
            folder in which the IDE's ``Build'' function will invoke the make command,
            so it should contain a makefile. It is expected that this makefile
            will build the whole project, so it is supposed to invoke all other makefiles,
            either directly or indirectly. By default, the build root folder is
            the project root.  This is usually fine, but if you really need to change
            the project build root, overwrite the ``Build location'' setting
            in the ``C/&Cpp; Build'' page of the same dialog.
            </para>

            <note>
            All generated makefiles will be named [[Makefile]];
            custom makefiles are also expected to have this name.
            </note>
        </sect3>

        <sect3><title>Source Folders</title>
            <para>In addition to makefiles, you also need to specify where your &Cpp; files are
            located (source folders). This is usually the [[src]] folder of the project,
            or, for small projects, the project root. It is also possible to exclude folders
            from a source folder. The controls on the right-bottom part of the dialog
            (``Source'' group) allow you to set up source folders and exclusions on
            the project. Source files that are outside source folders or are in an excluded
            folder will be ignored by both the IDE and the build process.
            </para>

            <note>
            Source folders and exclusions that you configure on this page actually
            modify the contents of the ``Source Location'' tab of the ``&Cpp; General | Paths and Symbols''
            page of the project properties dialog; the changes will affect all build
            configurations.
            </note>

            <para>Automatically created makefiles are by default ``deep'', meaning that
            they include all (non-excluded) source files under them in the build.
            That is, a source file will be included in the build if it is both under
            a source folder and covered by a makefile. (This applies to automatically
            generated makefiles; the IDE has obviously no control over the behaviour
            of custom makefiles.)
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3><title>Makefile Generation</title>
            <para>Makefile generation for the selected folder can be configured on the
            ``Makemake Options'' dialog, which can be brought up by clicking the
            ``Options'' button on the page. The dialog is described in the next section.
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3><title>Command-line Build</title>
            <para>To re-create your makefiles on the command line, you can export the
            settings by pressing the ``Export'' button. This action will create a file
            with the name [[makemakefiles]]. After exporting, execute [[make -f makemakefiles]]
            from the command line.
            </para>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
        <title>Configuring Makefile Generation for a Folder</title>

        <para>Makefile generation for a folder can be configured in the ``Makemake Options''
        dialog. To access the dialog, open the ``OMNeT++ | Makemake'' page in the
        ``Project Properties'' dialog, select the folder, make sure makefile generation
        is enabled for it, and click the ``Options'' button.
        </para>

        <para>The following sections describe each page of the dialog.
        </para>

        <sect3>
          <title>The ``Target'' Tab</title>
          <para>On the first, ``Target'' tab of the dialog, you can specify how the final
          target of the makefile is created.
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                ``Target type'': The build target can be an executable, a shared or static library,
                or the linking step may be omitted altogether.
                Makemake options: [[--make-so]], [[--make-lib]], [[--nolink]]
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                ``Export this shared/static library for other projects'': This option is observed
                if a library (shared or static) is selected as target type, and works in conjunction
                with the ``Link with libraries exported from referenced projects'' option on the ``Link'' tab.
                Namely, referencing projects will automatically link with this library if both the library is
                exported from this project AND linking with exported libraries is enabled in the referencing project.
                Makemake option: [[--meta:export-library]]
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                ``Target name'': You may set the target name. The default value is derived from the project name.
                Makemake option: [[-o]] (If you are building a debug configuration, the target name will be implicitly
                suffixed by the [[_dbg]] string.)
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                ``Output directory'': The output directory specifies where the object files and the final target
                will be created, relative to the project root. Makemake option: [[-O]]
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
          <picture file="pictures/CPP-ConfigureProject2.png">Target definition</picture>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>The ``Scope'' Tab</title>
          <picture file="pictures/CPP-ConfigureProject.png">Scope of makefile</picture>
          <para>
            The ``Scope'' tab allows you to configure the scope of the makefile and which source files
            will be included.</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              ``Deep compile'': When enabled, the makefile will compile the source files in the whole
              subdirectory tree (except excluded folders and folder covered by other makefiles).
              When disabled, the makefile only compiles sources in the makefile's folder.
              Makemake option: [[--deep]]
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              ``Recursive make'': When enabled, the build will invoke make in all descendant folders
              that are configured to contain a makefile.
              Makemake option: [[--meta:recurse]] (resolves to multiple [[-d]] options)
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              ``More &raquo; Additionally invoke make in the following directories'':
              If you want to invoke additional makefiles from this makefile, specify which directories
              should be visited (relative to this makefile). This option is useful if you want to
              invoke makefiles outside this source tree.
              Makemake option: [[-d]]
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>The ``Compile'' Tab</title>
          <commercial>
            <picture file="pictures/CPP-ConfigureProject3-omnest.png">Compiler options</picture>
          </commercial>
          <noncommercial>
            <picture file="pictures/CPP-ConfigureProject3-omnetpp.png">Compiler options</picture>
          </noncommercial>
          <para>
            The ``Compile'' tab allows you to adjust the parameters passed to the compiler during the build
            process.</para>
          <para>Settings that affect the include path:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              ``Export include path for other projects'' makes this project's include path
              available for other dependent projects. This is usually required if your
              project expects that other independent models will extend it in the future.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              ``Add include paths exported from referenced projects'' allows a dependent project
              to use header files from the dependencies if those projects have exported their
              include path (i.e. the above option was turned on.)
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              ``Add include dirs and other compile options from enabled project features'':
              Project features may require additional include paths and defines to compile
              properly. Enabling this option will add those command line arguments (specified
              in the ``.oppfeatures'' file) to the compiler command line.
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>Source files:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              ``&Cpp; file extension'': You can specify the source file extension you are
              using in the project ([[.cc]] or [[.cpp]]). We recommend that you use [[.cc]]
              in your projects. Makemake option: [[-e]]
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <commercial>
          <para>
              If you want to build a DLL on Windows using the Microsoft Visual Studio Clang/C2 compiler,
              symbols you want to use from other code need to be explicitly exported from the DLL.
              Functions, variables and classes must be marked with [[__declspec(dllexport)]] when the DLL is
              compiled, and with [[__declspec(dllimport)]] when you reference them from external code.
              This is achieved by defining a macro which expands differently in the two cases. The &Omnetpp;
              convention is to name the macro [[FOO_API]], where ``FOO'' is your project's short name.
              The macro should be defined as follows:</para>
          <screen>
#if defined(FOO_EXPORT)
#  define FOO_API OPP_DLLEXPORT
#elif defined(FOO_IMPORT)
#  define FOO_API OPP_DLLIMPORT
#else
#  define FOO_API
#endif
          </screen>
          <para>and the above definition should be manually placed into a header file which is included
          by all headers where the macro is used.
          [[OPP_DLLEXPORT]] and [[OPP_DLLIMPORT]] are provided by [[&lt;omnetpp.h&gt;]], and
          [[FOO_EXPORT]] / [[FOO_IMPORT]] that control the macro expansion will be provided by the
          generated makefile via a compile option.
          </para>
          <para>Settings for Windows DLLs:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              ``Force compiling object files for use in DLLs'': If the makefile target is a DLL,
              &Omnetpp; automatically compiles the sources for DLL (defines the [[FOO_EXPORT]] macro, etc.),
              regardless of the state of this option. Rather, this option is useful if the makefile target
              is ``not'' a DLL, but the code compiled here will eventually end up in a DLL.
              Makemake option: [[-S]]
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              ``DLL export/import symbol'': Name for the DLL import/export symbol, i.e. [[FOO]] in the above examples.
              Makemake option: [[-p]]
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          </commercial>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>The ``Link'' Tab</title>
          <para>
            Link options allow the user to fine-tune the linking steps at the end of the build process.
          </para>
          <picture file="pictures/CPP-ConfigureProject4.png">Linker options</picture>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              ``Link with libraries exported from referenced projects'': If your project references other projects
              that build static or dynamic libraries, you can instruct the linker to
              automatically link with those libraries by enabling this option. The libraries from
              the other projects must be exported via the ``Export this shared/static library for other projects''
              option on the ``Target'' tab.
              Makemake option: [[--meta:use-exported-libs]]
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              ``Add libraries and other linker options from enabled project features'':
              Project features may require additional libraries and linker options to build
              properly. Enabling this option will add those command line arguments (specified
              in the ``.oppfeatures'' file) to the linker command line.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              ``User interface libraries to link with'': If the makefile target is an executable, you may
              specify which &Omnetpp; user interface libraries (Cmdenv, Tkenv, or both) should be linked
              into the program.
              Makemake option: [[-u]]
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              ``More &raquo; Additional libraries to link with'': This box allows you to specify
              additional libraries to link with. Specify the library name without its path, possible prefix ([[lib]])
              and file extension, and also without the [[-l]] option. The library must be on the linker path;
              the linker path can be edited on the ``Library Paths'' tab of the ``C/&Cpp; General | Paths and Symbols''
              page of the ``Project Properties'' dialog.
              Makemake option: [[-l]]
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              ``More &raquo; Additional objects to link with'': Additional object files and libraries can be
              specified here. The files must be given with their full paths and file extension. Wildcards
              and makefile macros are also accepted. Example: [[$O/subdir/*.o]].
              Makemake option: none (files will become plain makemake arguments)
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>The ``Custom'' Tab</title>
          <para>The ``Custom'' tab allows the customization of the makefiles by inserting handwritten makefile
            fragments into the automatically generated makefile. This lets you contribute additional targets,
            rules, variables, etc.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              ``Makefrag'': If the folder contains a file named [[makefrag]],
              its contents will be automatically copied into the generated makefile, just above the
              first target rule. [[makefrag]] allows you to customize the generated makefile to some extent;
              for example, you can add new targets (e.g. to generate documentation or run a test suite),
              new rules (e.g. to generate source files during the build), override the default target,
              add new dependencies to existing targets, overwrite variables, etc.
              The dialog lets you edit the contents of the [[makefrag]] file directly (it will be saved
              when you accept the dialog).
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              ``More &raquo; Fragment files to include'': Here, it is possible to explicitly specify
              a list of makefile fragment files to include, instead of the default
              [[makefrag]].
              Makemake option: [[-i]]
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>The ``Preview'' Tab</title>
          <para>The ``Preview'' tab displays the command line options that will be passed to
            [[opp_makemake]] to generate the makefile. It consists of two parts:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              ``Makemake options'': This is an ``editable'' list of makefile generation options.
              Most options map directly to checkboxes, edit fields and other controls on the
              previous tabs of the dialog. For example, if you check the ``Deep compile'' checkbox
              on the ``Scope'' tab, the [[--deep]] option will be added to the command line.
              Conversely, if you delete [[--deep]] from the command line options, that will cause
              the ``Deep compile'' checkbox to be unchecked.
              Some options are directly [[opp_makemake]] options, others are "meta" options
              that will be resolved to one or more [[opp_makemake]] options; see below.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              ``Makemake options modified with CDT settings and with meta-options resolved'':
              This is a read-only text field, displayed for information purposes only.
              Not all options in the above options list are directly understood by [[opp_makemake]];
              namely, the options that start with [[--meta:]] denote higher-level features offered
              by the IDE only. Meta options will be translated to [[opp_makemake]] options by the IDE.
              For example, [[--meta:auto-include-path]] will be resolved by the IDE to multiple
              [[-I]] options, one for each directory in the &Cpp; source trees of the project.
              This field shows the [[opp_makemake]] options after the resolution of the meta options.
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
        <title>Project References and Makefile Generation</title>

        <para>When your project references another project (say the INET Framework),
        your project's build will be affected in the following way:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            Include path: Source folders in referenced projects will be automatically added
            to the include path of your makefile if the ``Add include paths exported from
            referenced projects'' option on the ``Compile'' tab is checked where the
            referenced projects also enable the ``Export include path for other projects''
            option.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Linking: If the ``Link with libraries exported from referenced projects'' option on the
            ``Link'' tab is enabled, then the makefile target will be linked with those libraries
            in referenced projects that have the ``Export this shared/static library for other projects''
            option checked on the ``Target'' tab.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            NED types: NED types defined in a referenced project are automatically available
            in referencing projects.
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Project Features</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Motivation</title>
      <para>
        Long compile times are often an inconvenience when working with large
        &Omnetpp;-based model frameworks like the INET Framework. The IDE feature
        named ``Project Features'' lets you reduce build times by excluding or
        disabling parts of the model framework that you do not use for your
        simulation study. For example, when you are working on mobile ad-hoc simulations in INET,
        you can disable the compilation of Ethernet, IPv6/MIPv6, MPLS, and other
        unrelated protocol models. The word ``feature'' refers to a piece of
        the project codebase that can be turned off as a whole.
      </para>
      <para>
        Additional benefits of project features include a less cluttered model palette
        in the NED editor, being able to exclude code that does not compile on your system,
        and enforcing cleaner separation of unrelated parts in the model framework.
      </para>
      <note>
        A similar effect could also achieved via breaking up the model framework (e.g. INET)
        into several smaller projects, but that would cause other kinds of inconveniences for
        model developers and users alike.
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>What is a Project Feature</title>
      <para>
        Features can be defined per project. As already mentioned, a feature is a piece of the
        project codebase that can be turned off as a whole, that is, excluded from the &Cpp; sources
        (and thus from the build) and also from NED. Feature definitions are typically written
        and distributed by the author of the project; end users are only presented with the
        option of enabling/disabling those features. A feature definition contains:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          ``ID'', which is a unique identifier inside the feature definition file.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          ``Feature name,'' for example [["UDP"]] or [["Mobility examples"]].
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          ``Feature description.'' This is a few sentences of text describing what the feature
          is or does; for example [["Implementation of the UDP protocol"]].
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          ``Labels.'' This is list of labels or keywords that facilitate grouping or finding features.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          ``Initially enabled.'' This is a boolean flag that determines the initial enablement
          of the feature.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          ``Required features.'' Some features may be built on top of others; for example, a HMIPv6
          protocol implementation relies on MIPv6, which in turn relies on IPv6. Thus, HMIPv6 can
          only be enabled if MIPv6 and IPv6 are enabled as well. This is a space-separated list of
          feaure IDs.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          ``NED packages.'' This is a space-separated list of NED package names that identify the
          code that implements the feature. When you disable the feature, NED types defined in those
          packages and their subpackages will be excluded; also, &Cpp; code in the folders that correspond
          to the packages (i.e. in the same folders as excluded NED files) will also be excluded.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          ``Extra &Cpp; source folders.'' If the feature contains &Cpp; code that lives outside NED source
          folders (nontypical), those folders are listed here.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          ``Compile options,'' for example [[-DWITH_IPv6]]. When the feature is enabled, the compiler
          options listed here are either added to the compiler command line of all &Cpp; files
          or they can be used to generate a header file containing all these defines
          so that header file can be included in all &Cpp; files. A typical use of this field is
          defining symbols ([[WITH_xxx]]] that allows you to write conditional code
          that only compiles when a given feature is enabled. Currently only the [[-D]] option
          (``define symbol'') is supported here.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          ``Linker options.'' When the feature is enabled, the linker options listed here are added
          to the linker command line. A typical use of this field is linking with additional
          libraries that the feature's code requires, for example libavcodec.
          Currently only the [[-l]] option (``link with library'') is supported here.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The Project Features Dialog</title>
      <para>
        Features can be viewed, enabled and disabled on the ``Project Features'' page of the
        ``Project Properties'' dialog. The ``Project | Project Features...'' menu item
        is a direct shortcut to this property page.
      </para>
      <picture file="pictures/CPP-Features.png">The Project Features page</picture>
      <para>
        The central area of the dialog page lists the features defined for the project.
        Hovering the mouse over a list item will show the description and other fields
        of the feature in a tooltip window. Check an item to enable the feature, and uncheck
        to disable.
      </para>
      <para>
        When you enable a feature that requires other features to work, the dialog
        will ask for permission to enable the required features as well. Also, if you disable
        a feature that others depend on, they will be disabled, too.
      </para>
      <para>
        The ``Apply'', ``OK'' and ``Cancel'' buttons work as expected. ``Restore Defaults''
        restores the features to their initial state (see the ``Initially enabled'' attribute above).
      </para>
      <para>
        Above the list there is a notification area in the dialog. If the IDE detects that
        your project's configuration is inconsistent with the feature enablements, it will display
        a warning there, and offer a way to automatically fix the problems. Fixing means that
        the IDE will adjust the project's NED and &Cpp; settings to make them consistent
        with the feature enablements. Such check is also performed just before build.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>What Happens When You Enable/Disable a Feature</title>
      <para>
        When you enable or disable a feature on the ``Project Features'' page, a number of project
        settings will be modified:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          NED package exclusions. This corresponds to the contents of the ``Excluded package subtrees''
          list on the ``NED Source Folders'' property page. When a feature is disabled,
          its NED packages will be excluded (added to the list), and vice versa.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          &Cpp; folder exclusions. This can be viewed/edited on the ``Makemake'' property page, and
          also on the ``Source Location'' tab of the ``C/&Cpp; General > Paths and Symbols''
          property page.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Compile options. For example, if the feature defines preprocessor symbols ([[-DWITH_xxx]]),
          they can be used to generate a header file that contains the enabled macro definitions and
          that file can be included in all &Cpp; files.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Linker options. For example, if the feature defines additional libraries to link with,
          they will be displayed on the ``Libraries'' tab of the ``C/&Cpp; General > Paths and Symbols''
          property page.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <note>
        Feature enablements are saved to the [[.oppfeaturestate]] file in the project root.
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Using Features from Command Line</title>
      <para>
        ``Project Features'' can be easily configured from the IDE, but command line tools
        ([[opp_makemake]], etc.) can also use them with the help of the [[opp_featuretool]]
        command.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you want to build the project from the command line with the same feature
        combination the IDE is using, you need to generate the makefiles with the same [[opp_makemake]]
        options that the IDE uses in that feature combination. The [[opp_featuretool makemakeargs]]
        command (executed in the project's root directory) will show all the required
        arguments that you need to specify for the  [[opp_makemake]] command to
        build the same output as the IDE. This allows you to keep the same
        features enabled no matter how you build your project.
      </para>
      <para>
        Alternatively, you can choose ``Export'' on the ``Makemake'' page, and copy/paste the
        options from the generated [[makemakefiles]] file. This method is
        not recommended, because you must redo it manually each time after changing
        the enablement state of a feature.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The [[.oppfeatures]] File</title>
      <para>
        Project features are defined in the [[.oppfeatures]] file in your project's
        root directory. This is an XML file, and it currently has to be written by hand
        (there is no specialized editor for it).
      </para>

      <para>
        The root element is [[&lt;features&gt;]], and it may have several [[&lt;feature&gt;]]
        child elements, each defining a project feature. Attributes of the [[&lt;features&gt;]]
        element define the root(s) of the source folder(s) ([[cppSourceRoots]]) and the name of a
        generated header file that contains all defines specified by the [[compilerFlags]]
        attribute in the enabled features. The fields of a feature
        are represented with XML attributes; attribute names are [[id]], [[name]],
        [[description]], [[initiallyEnabled]], [[requires]], [[labels]], [[nedPackages]],
        [[extraSourceFolders]], [[compileFlags]] and [[linkerFlags]]. Items within attributes
        that represent lists ([[requires]], [[labels]], etc.) are separated by spaces.
      </para>

      <para>
        Here is an example feature from the INET Framework:
      </para>

<screen><![CDATA[
<features cppSourceRoots="src" definesFile="src/inet/features.h">
    <feature
        id="TCP_common"
        name="TCP Common"
        description = "The common part of TCP implementations"
        initiallyEnabled = "true"
        requires = ""
        labels = ""
        nedPackages = "
                       inet.transport.tcp_common
                       inet.applications.tcpapp
                       inet.util.headerserializers.tcp
                      "
        extraSourceFolders = ""
        compileFlags = "-DWITH_TCP_COMMON"
        linkerFlags = ""
    />
]]></screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>How to Introduce a Project Feature</title>
      <para>
        If you plan to introduce a project feature in your project, here's what you'll need
        to do:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          Isolate the code that implements the feature into a separate source directory
          (or several directories). This is because only whole folders can be
          declared as part of a feature, individual source files cannot.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Check the remainder of the project. If you find source lines that reference
          code from the new feature, use conditional compilation ([[#ifdef WITH_YOURFEATURE]])
          to make sure that code compiles (and either works sensibly or throws an error)
          when the new feature is disabled. (Your feature should define the [[WITH_YOURFEATURE]]
          symbol, i.e. [[-DWITH_YOURFEATURE]] will need to be added to the feature compile flags.)
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Add the feature description into the [[.oppfeatures]] file of your project
          including the required feature dependencies.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Test. At the minimum, test that your project compiles at all, both with the
          new feature enabled and disabled. More thorough, automated tests can be built using
          [[opp_featuretool]].
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Project Files</title>
    <para>
      Eclipse, CDT and the &Omnetpp; IDE uses several files in the project to store settings.
      These files are located in the project root directory, and they are normally
      hidden by the IDE in the ``Project Explorer View''. The files include:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        [[.project]] : Eclipse stores the general project properties in this file including project name,
        dependencies from other projects, and project type (i.e. whether &Omnetpp;-specific
        features are supported or this is only a generic Eclipse project).
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        [[.cproject]] : This file contains settings specific to &Cpp; development, including
        the build configurations; and per-configuration settings such as source folder locations
        and exclusions, include paths, linker paths, symbols; the build command, error parsers,
        debugger settings and so on.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        [[.oppbuildspec]] : Contains settings specific to &Omnetpp;.
        This file stores per-folder makefile generation settings that can be configured
        on the ``Makemake'' page of the ``Project Properties'' dialog.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        [[.oppfeatures]] : Optionally contains the definitions of project features.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        [[.oppfeaturestate]] : Optionally contains the current enablement state of the features.
        (We do not recommend keeping this file under version control.)
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        [[.nedfolders]] : Contains the names of NED source folders;
        this is the information that can be configured on the ``NED Source Folders'' page
        of the ``Project Properties'' dialog.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        [[.nedexclusions]] : Contains the names of excluded NED packages.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      If you are creating a project where no &Cpp; support is needed (i.e. you are using an existing
      precompiled simulation library and you edit only NED and Ini files), the [[.cproject]] and
      [[.oppbuildspec]] files will not be present in your project.
    </para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
