<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "custom-docbook.dtd">
<chapter id="ide-extensions">
  <title>Extending the IDE</title>
  <para>There are several ways to extend the functionality of the &Omnetpp; IDE. The
    Simulation IDE is based on the Eclipse platform, and extends it with new
    editors, views, wizards, and other functionality.
  </para>
  <sect1>
    <title>Installing New Features</title>
    <para>
    Because the IDE is based on the Eclipse platform, it is possible to add additional features
    that are available for Eclipse. The installation procedure is exactly the same as with
    a standard Eclipse distribution. Choose the ``Help | Install New Software...'' menu item
    and select an existing Update Site to work with or add a new Site (using the site URL)
    to the Available Software Sites.
    After the selection you can browse and install the packages the site offers.
    </para>
    <para>To read about installing new software into your IDE, please visit the ``Updating and
    installing software'' topic in the ``Workbench User Guide''. You can find the online help system
    in the ``Help | Help Contents'' menu.
    </para>
    <tip>
    There are thousands of useful components and extensions for Eclipse.
    The best places to start looking for extensions are the Eclipse Marketplace
    (http://marketplace.eclipse.org/) and the Eclipse Plugins info site
    (http://www.eclipse-plugins.info).
    </tip>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Adding New Wizards</title>
    <para>
    The Simulation IDE makes it possible to contribute new wizards into the wizard dialogs
    under the ``File | New'' menu, without writing Java code or requiring any knowledge
    of Eclipse internals. Wizards can create new simulation projects, new simulations,
    new NED files or other files by using templates, or perform export or import.
    Wizard code is placed under the ``templates'' folder of an &Omnetpp; project, which
    makes it easy to distribute wizards with the model. When the user imports and opens
    a project which contains wizards, the wizards will become automatically available.
    </para>
    <tip>The way of creating wizards is documented in the ``IDE Customization Guide''.</tip>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Project Specific Extensions</title>
    <para>
       It is possible to install an Eclipse plug-in by creating a ``plugins'' folder
       in an &Omnetpp; project, and copying the plug-in JAR file there. (This mechanism is
       implemented as part of the Simulation IDE, and does not work in generic Eclipse installations
       or with non-&Omnetpp; projects.  This extension mechanism allows the distribution
       of model specific IDE extensions together with a simulation project,
       without requiring the end user to do extra deployment steps to install the plug-in.
       Plugins and wizards - distributed with a project - are automatically activated when the host
       project is opened.
    </para>
    <para>
       Eclipse plug-in JAR files can be created using the ``Plugin Development Environment''.
       The &Omnetpp; IDE does not contain the ``PDE'' by default, however it can be easily installed if need.
    </para>
    <tip>Read the ``&Omnetpp; IDE Development Guide'' for more information about how to install the PDE, and
    how to develop plug-in extensions for the IDE.</tip>
  </sect1>

</chapter>