<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="ini-editor">
  <title>Editing INI Files</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      In OMNeT++, simulation models are parameterized and configured for execution using
      configuration files with the .ini extension, called ini files. Ini files are text
      files which can be edited using any text editor. However, OMNeT++ 4.0 introduces a
      tool expressly designed for editing ini files. The Inifile Editor is part of the
      OMNeT++ IDE, and it can very efficiently assist the user in authoring ini files,
      because it has detailed knowledge of the simulation model, the ini file syntax, and
      the available configuration options.
    </para>
    <note>
      The syntax and features of ini files have changed since OMNeT++ 3.x as well.
      These changes are summarized in the document titled "Configuring Simulations in
      OMNeT++ 4.0." TBD
    </note>
    <para>
      The Inifile Editor is a dual-mode editor: the configuration can be edited using
      forms and dialogs, or as plain text. Forms are organized around topics like general
      setup, Cmdenv, Tkenv, output files, extensions and so on. Connected with the NED
      editor… TBD
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Creating INI files</title>
    <para>wizard… TBD</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Using the INI File Editor</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Editing in form mode</title>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Editing in text mode</title>
      <para />
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Associated Views</title>
    <para>
      There are several views related to the INI editor. These views can be displayed (if
      not already open) by choosing Window|Show View in the menu.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Outline View</title>
      <para>
        The Outline View allows an overview of the current NED file. Clicking on an
        element will focus the corresponding element in the text or graphical view. In
        graphical view, it has limited editing functionality. You can delete an object
        here (right click/delete), and the order of elements can be rearranged by dragging
        them.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Problems View</title>
      <para>
        The Problems View contains error and warning messages generated by the parser.
        Double-clicking a line will open the problematic file and move to the appropriate
        marker.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Module Hierarchy View</title>
      <para>
        The Module Hierarchy View shows the contained submodules, several levels deep.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>NED Inheritance View</title>
      <para>TBD</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Parameters View</title>
      <para>
        The Parameters View shows parameters of the selected module, including inherited
        parameters.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
