<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>The OMNeT++ simulation IDE is based on the Eclipse Framework,
for which manuals are available on 
<ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/">www.eclipse.org</ulink>. While
this flexible and easy to use platform makes the OMNeT++ simulation
IDE inherently more easy to use, it helps to have a concise
reference on what the system is capable of and just how you can
reach the appropriate section. In developing the OMNeT++ IDE, we
followed guidelines for making Eclipse plugins, integrating the
functionality available in separate modules in OMNeT++ 3.3 into one
comprehensive system. This approach has many benefits. The
environment will be instantly recognizable to those at home with
the Eclipse system, but sections will also become quickly familiar
to users of earlier versions of OMNeT++. Having the system's
functions interconnected this way brings more power and flexibility
to the system.</para>

<para>The OMNeT++ 4.0 Integrated Development Environment extends
Eclipse with new editors, views, wizards, and other functionality.
OMNeT++ adds functionality for creating and configuring models (NED
and .ini files), performing batch executions and analyzing the
simulation results, while Eclipse provides C++ editing, CVS/SVN
integration and optionally other features (UML modeling,
bug-tracker integration, database access, etc) via various
open-source and commercial plug-ins.</para>

<sect1>
<title>The Workbench</title>
<para>The Eclipse Editor layout consists of various Views and
Editors. These are collected into Perspectives that define which
Views and Editors are visible, and how they are sized and
positioned.</para>

<para>Eclipse is a very flexible system. You can move, resize, hide
and show various panels, editors and navigators. This allows you to
customize the IDE to your liking, but it also makes it more
difficult to describe. First, we need to make sure that we are
looking at the same thing.</para>

<para>TODO: Ensure there is a default view available to load, and
describe it here.</para>

<picture file="pictures/1.0_Select_Perspective.png">Selecting the
OMNeT++ perspective in Eclipse</picture>

<para>Most interface elements within Eclipse are movable, can be
docked to various palettes or sections. The whole workspace is
configurable, so you can construct your own workspace, but we will
use the following layout throughout this manual, to get familiar
with the various sections:</para>

<picture file="pictures/2.0_IDE_default_layout_view.png">OMNeT++
IDE with README.txt selected in the Navigator</picture>

<para>The Navigator on the top left part of the screen shows a
hierarchical view of the various open projects in your workspace.
In the example above, the "aloha" demo project is open, you can see
the various .NED, .ini and other files inside.</para>

<para>We double-clicked the README.txt file, and its contents are
loaded into the editor area. Eclipse automatically launches the
editor associated with a particular file type, so you can start
editing right away.</para>

<para>This view contains information on the particular object that
is selected.in the editor area, or one of the other views that
serve as a selection provider. In case of NED objects for example,
display-specific properties such as icons, colorization, position,
etc. Can be read and set here. Help is also available in the form
of code assist, where pressing CTRL+SPACE in one of the fields will
provide you with a list of selectable valid options for that field.
Some fields, such as the Icon property, or Color type properties
have graphical picker dialogs associated with them too.</para>

<para>A number of views are docked here. The Problems View
references code lines where Eclipse encountered a problem while
parsing. The Editor also provides visual feedback by placing a red
"X" icon in front of the line of code that is causing the
problem.</para>

<para>The Module Hierarchy View will show you what modules are
nested in the currently selected NED object.</para>

<para>The NED Parameters View lists all the parameters defined
inside the selected object, as well as the parameters that the
object inherited from other objects.</para>

<para>The Debug View contains debug output. This is a standard
Eclipse feature.</para>

<para>The Console View is where all console output will be
redirected to, if you run a simulation from within Eclipse.</para>

<para>The Event Log View will show you a list of events for a
simulation that has been executed.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>The Simulation Perspective</title>
<para>TBD</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Creating OMNeT++ Projects</title>
<para>TBD</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Getting Help</title>
<para>TBD</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
