<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "custom-docbook.dtd">
<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
    The &Omnetpp;
    simulation IDE is based on the Eclipse platform and extends it with new editors, views, wizards, and
    other functionality. &Omnetpp;
    adds functionality for creating and configuring models (NED and INI files), performing batch executions
    and analyzing the simulation results, while Eclipse provides &Cpp; editing, SVN/GIT integration and
    other optional features (UML modeling, bug-tracker integration, database access, etc.) via various
    open-source and commercial plug-ins. The environment will be instantly recognizable to those at home with
    the Eclipse platform.
  </para>

  <sect1>
    <title>The Workbench</title>
    <para>The Eclipse main window consists of various Views and Editors. These are collected into
      Perspectives that define which Views and Editors are visible and how they are sized and positioned.
    </para>
    <para>Eclipse is a very flexible system. You can move, resize, hide and show various panels,
      editors and navigators. This allows you to customize the IDE to your liking, but it also makes it more
      difficult to describe. First, we need to make sure that we are looking at the same thing.</para>
    <para>The &Omnetpp;
      IDE provides a "Simulation perspective" to work with simulation-related NED, INI and MSG files. To
      switch to the simulation perspective, select ``Window | Open Perspective | Simulation''.
    </para>
    <picture file="pictures/Intro-SelectPerspective.png">Selecting the "Simulation Perspective" in Eclipse</picture>
    <para>Most interface elements within Eclipse are can be moved or docked freely so you can
      construct your own workbench to fit your needs.</para>
    <picture file="pictures/Intro-DefaultLayout.png">Default
      layout of the &Omnetpp;
      IDE
    </picture>
    <para>The ``Project Explorer'' on the top left part of the screen shows the projects
    and their content in your workspace. In the example above, the ``queueinglib'' demo project is open.
      You can see the various [[.ned]], [[.ini]] and other files inside. A number
      of views are docked at the bottom of the window.</para>
    <para>The screenshot shows the open README.txt file in the editor area. When a user double-clicks on a file, Eclipse
      automatically launches the editor associated with that particular file type.
    </para>
    <para>The ``Properties View'' contains information on the particular object that is selected in the
      editor area, or one of the other views that serve as a selection provider.
      The ``Problems View'' references code lines where Eclipse encountered problems.</para>
    <para>Several &Omnetpp;-specific
      views exist that can be used during development. We will discuss how you can use them
      effectively in a later chapter. You can open any View by selecting ``Window | Show View''
      from the menu.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Workspaces</title>
    <para>
      A workspace is basically a directory where all your projects are located. You may create and use several
      workspaces and switch between them as needed. During the first run, the &Omnetpp;
      IDE offers to open the samples directory as the workspace, so you will be able to experiment with the
      available examples immediately. Once you start working on your own projects, we recommend that you create
      your own workspace by selecting ``File | Switch Workspace | Other'' . You can switch between workspaces,
      as necessary. Please be aware that the &Omnetpp;
      IDE restarts with each switch in workspaces. This is normal. You can browse workspace content
      in the ``Project Explorer'', ``Navigator'', ``C/&Cpp; Projects'' and similar views. We recommend
      using ``Project Explorer''.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>The Simulation Perspective</title>
    <para>The &Omnetpp;
      IDE defines the ``Simulation Perspective'' so that it is specifically geared towards the design of simulations. The
      ``Simulation Perspective'' is simply a set of conveniently selected views, arranged to make
      the creation of NED, INI and MSG files easier. If you are working with INI and NED files a lot, we
      recommend selecting this perspective. Other perspectives are optimized for different tasks like &Cpp;
      development or debugging.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Configuring &Omnetpp; Preferences
    </title>
    <para>The &Omnetpp;
      IDE preferences dialog is available through the standard preferences menu, which is under the main Window menu item.
      These settings are global and shared between all projects. The &Omnetpp; install locations are
      automatically filled in for you after installation. The default settings for the NED documentation generation
      assume that the PATH environment variable is already set, so that third party tools can be found. The license
      configuration settings specify the preferred license type or a custom license text. The IDE will copy the
      license into new files and projects. The license will also be shown in the generated NED documentation.
      <picture file="pictures/Intro-Preferences.png">
        Configuring &Omnetpp; preferences
      </picture>
      Use the Browse buttons to find files or folders easily. Specify full path for executables if you do not want
      to extend the PATH environment variable.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Creating &Omnetpp;
      Projects
    </title>
    <para>
      In Eclipse, all files are within projects, so you will need a suitable project first. The project needs to be
      one designated as an &Omnetpp; Project (in Eclipse lingo, it should have the &Omnetpp; Nature).
      The easiest way to create such a project is to use a wizard. Choose ``File|New|&Omnetpp; Project...''
      from the menu, specify a project name, and click the ``Finish'' button. If you do not plan
      to write simple modules, you may unselect the ``&Cpp; Support'' checkbox which will disable all &Cpp;
      related features for the project.
      <picture file="pictures/Intro-NewProjectWizard.png">
        Creating a new &Omnetpp; project
      </picture>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Project References</title>
    <para>
      Most aspects of a project can be configured in the ``Project Properties'' dialog.
      The dialog is accessible via the ``Project | Properties...'' menu item, or by right-clicking
      the project in ``Project Explorer'' and choosing ``Properties'' from the context menu.
    </para>
    <para>
      An important Eclipse concept is that a project may reference other projects in the workspace;
      project references can be configured in the ``Project References'' page of the properties
      dialog. To update the list of referenced projects, simply check those projects in the list
      that your project depends on, then click ``Apply''. Note that circular references are not allowed
      (i.e. the dependency graph must be a tree).
    </para>
    <picture file="pictures/Intro-ProjectReferences.png">Setting project dependencies</picture>
    <para>
      In the &Omnetpp; IDE, all NED types, &Cpp; code and build artifacts (executables, libraries) in a project
      are available to other projects that reference the given project.
     </para>
    <note>
      To see an example of project references, check the [[queuenet]] and [[queueinglib]] example projects.
      In this example, [[queuenet]] references [[queueinglib]]. [[Queuinglib]] provides simple
      modules (NED files, and a prebuilt shared library that contains the code of the simple modules),
      and makes those modules available to [[queuenet]] that contains simulations (networks and ini files)
      built from them.
    </note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Getting Help</title>
    <para>
      You may access the online help system from the ``Help | Help Contents'' menu item. The &Omnetpp;
      IDE is built on top of Eclipse, so if you are not familiar with Eclipse, we recommend reading
      the ``Workbench User Guide'' and the ``C/&Cpp; Development User Guide'' before starting to use &Omnetpp;-specific
      features.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
