<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "custom-docbook.dtd">
<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
    The &Omnetpp;
    simulation IDE is based on the Eclipse platform, and extends it with new editors, views, wizards, and
    other functionality. &Omnetpp;
    adds functionality for creating and configuring models (NED and INI files), performing batch executions
    and analyzing the simulation results, while Eclipse provides C++ editing, CVS/SVN integration and
    optionally other features (UML modeling, bug-tracker integration, database access, etc) via various
    open-source and commercial plug-ins. The environment will be instantly recognizable to those at home with
    the Eclipse platform. 
  </para>
  <sect1>
    <title>The Workbench</title>
    <para>The Eclipse main window consists of various Views and Editors. These are collected into
      Perspectives that define which Views and Editors are visible, and how they are sized and positioned.
    </para>
    <para>Eclipse is a very flexible system. You can move, resize, hide and show various panels,
      editors and navigators. This allows you to customize the IDE to your liking, but it also makes it more
      difficult to describe. First, we need to make sure that we are looking at the same thing.</para>
    <para>The &Omnetpp;
      IDE provides a "Simulation perspective" to work with simulation related NED, INI and MSG files. To
      switch to the simulation perspective select ``Window | Open Perspective | Simulation''. 
    </para>
    <picture file="pictures/Intro-SelectPerspective.png">Selecting the Simulation perspective in Eclipse</picture>
    <para>Most interface elements within Eclipse are freely movable or dockable so you can 
      construct your own workbench, to fit your needs:</para>
    <picture file="pictures/Intro-DefaultLayout.png">Default
      layout of the &Omnetpp;
      IDE 
    </picture>
    <para>The ``Project Explorer'' on the top left part of the screen shows the projects 
    and their content in your workspace. In the example above, the ``queueinglib'' demo project is open.
      You can see the various [[.ned]], [[.ini]] and other files inside. A number 
      of views are docked at the bottom of the window.</para>
    <para>The screenshot shows the README.txt file opened in the editor area. On double click Eclipse
      automatically launches the editor associated with a particular file type.
    </para>
    <para>The ``Properties View'' contains information on the particular object that is selected in the
      editor area, or one of the other views that serve as a selection provider.
      The ``Problems View'' references code lines where Eclipse encountered a problem.</para>
    <para>Several &Omnetpp;
      specific view exist that can be used during development. We will discuss how you can use them
      effectively in a later chapter. You can open any View by selecting ``Window | Show View''
      from the menu. 
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Workspaces</title>
    <para>
      A workspace is basically a directory where all your projects are located. You may create and use several
      workspaces and switch between them as needed. At the first run the &Omnetpp;
      IDE offers to open the samples directory as the workspace so you will be able to experiment with the
      provided examples immediately. Once you start working on your own projects we recommend that you create
      your own workspace by selecting ``File | Switch Workspace | Other'' . You can switch between workspaces
      whenever you need. Please be aware that the &Omnetpp;
      IDE restarts on each workspace switch. This is normal behavior. Workspace content can be browsed
      in the ``Project Explorer'', ``Navigator'', ``C/C++ Projects'' and similar views. We recommend
      using ``Project Explorer''. 
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>The Simulation Perspective</title>
    <para>The &Omnetpp;
      IDE defines the ``Simulation Perspective'' specifically geared towards the design of simulations. The
      ``Simulation Perspective'' is nothing else just a set of views conveniently selected and arranged to make
      the creation of NED, INI and MSG files easier. If you are working with INI and NED files a lot we
      recommend to select this perspective. Other perspectives are optimized for different tasks like C++
      development or debugging. 
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Creating &Omnetpp;
      Projects 
    </title>
    <para>
      In Eclipse, all files are within projects, so first you need a suitable project. The project needs to be
      one designated as an &Omnetpp;
      Project. (In Eclipse lingo, it should have the &Omnetpp;
      Nature.) The easiest way to create such a project is to use a wizard: just choose ``File|New|&Omnetpp;
      Project...'' from the menu, specify a project name, and click the ``Finish'' button. If you do not plan
      to write simple modules, you may unselect the ``C++ Support'' checkbox which will disable all C++
      related features on the project. 
      <picture file="pictures/Intro-NewProjectWizard.png">
        Creating a new &Omnetpp;
        Project 
      </picture>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Getting Help</title>
    <para>
      You may access the online help system from the ``Help | Help Contents'' menu item. The &Omnetpp;
      IDE is built on top of Eclipse, so if your are not familiar with Eclipse, we recommend to read
      the [[Workbench User Guide]] and the [[C/C++ Development User Guide]] before starting to use &Omnetpp;
      specific features.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>