<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "custom-docbook.dtd">
<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
    The &Omnetpp; simulation IDE is based on the Eclipse Framework, for which manuals are
    available on
    <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/">www.eclipse.org</ulink>
    . While this flexible and easy to use platform makes the &Omnetpp; simulation IDE
    inherently more easy to use, it helps to have a concise reference on what the system
    is capable of and just how you can reach the appropriate section. In developing the
    &Omnetpp; IDE, we followed guidelines for making Eclipse plugins, integrating the
    functionality available in separate modules in &Omnetpp; 3.3 into one comprehensive
    system. This approach has many benefits. The environment will be instantly
    recognizable to those at home with the Eclipse system, but sections will also become
    quickly familiar to users of earlier versions of &Omnetpp;. Having the system's
    functions interconnected this way brings more power and flexibility to the system.
  </para>
  <para>The &Omnetpp; 4.0 Integrated Development Environment extends Eclipse with new
    editors, views, wizards, and other functionality. &Omnetpp; adds functionality for
    creating and configuring models (NED and .ini files), performing batch executions and
    analyzing the simulation results, while Eclipse provides C++ editing, CVS/SVN
    integration and optionally other features (UML modeling, bug-tracker integration,
    database access, etc) via various open-source and commercial plug-ins.</para>
  <sect1>
    <title>The Workbench</title>
    <para>The Eclipse Editor layout consists of various Views and Editors. These are
      collected into Perspectives that define which Views and Editors are visible, and how
      they are sized and positioned.</para>
    <para>Eclipse is a very flexible system. You can move, resize, hide and show
      various panels, editors and navigators. This allows you to customize the IDE to your
      liking, but it also makes it more difficult to describe. First, we need to make sure
      that we are looking at the same thing.</para>
    <para>TODO: Ensure there is a default view available to load, and describe it
      here.</para>
    <picture file="pictures/1.0_Select_Perspective.png">Selecting the &Omnetpp; perspective in Eclipse</picture>
    <para>Most interface elements within Eclipse are movable, can be docked to various
      palettes or sections. The whole workspace is configurable, so you can construct your
      own workspace, but we will use the following layout throughout this manual, to get
      familiar with the various sections:</para>
    <picture file="pictures/2.0_IDE_default_layout_view.png">&Omnetpp; IDE with README.txt selected in the Navigator</picture>
    <para>The Navigator on the top left part of the screen shows a hierarchical view of
      the various open projects in your workspace. In the example above, the "aloha" demo
      project is open, you can see the various .NED, .ini and other files inside.</para>
    <para>We double-clicked the README.txt file, and its contents are loaded into the
      editor area. Eclipse automatically launches the editor associated with a particular
      file type, so you can start editing right away.</para>
    <para>Property view contains information on the particular object that is
      selected in the editor area, or one of the other views that serve as a selection
      provider. In case of NED objects for example, display-specific properties such as
      icons, colorization, position, etc. Can be read and set here. Help is also available
      in the form of code assist, where pressing CTRL+SPACE in one of the fields will
      provide you with a list of selectable valid options for that field. Some fields,
      such as the Icon property, or Color type properties have graphical picker dialogs
      associated with them too.</para>
    <para>A number of views are docked at the bottom of the window. The Problems View
      references code lines where Eclipse encountered a problem while parsing. The Editor
      also provides visual feedback by placing a red "X" icon in front of the line of code
      that is causing the problem.</para>
    <para>The Module Hierarchy View will show you what modules are nested in the
      currently selected NED object.</para>
    <para>The NED Parameters View lists all the parameters defined inside the selected
      object, as well as the parameters that the object inherited from other objects.
    </para>
    <para>The Debug View contains all currently running simulations and allows to
      easily show the output of the given process. This is a standard Eclipse feature.
    </para>
    <para>The Console View is where all console output will be redirected to, if you
      run a simulation from within Eclipse.</para>
    <para>The Event Log View will show you a list of events for a simulation that has
      been executed.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Workspaces</title>
    <para>
      A workspace is basically a directory where all our projects are located. You may
      create and use several workspaces and switch between them as needed. At the first
      run the &Omnetpp; IDE offers to open the samples directory as the workspace so you
      will be able to experiment with the provided examples immediately. Once you start
      working on your own projects we recommend that you create your own workspace by
      selecting
      <guimenuitem>File | Switch Workspace | Other</guimenuitem>
      . You can switch between workspaces whenever you need. Please be aware that the
      &Omnetpp; IDE restarts on each workspace switch. This is normal behavior.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>The Simulation Perspective</title>
    <para>The &Omnetpp; IDE defines the Simulation perspective specifically geared
      towards the design of simulations. The simulation perspective is nothing else just a
      set of views conveniently selected and arranged to make the creation of NED, INI and
      MSG files easier. If you are working INI and NED files a lot we recommend to select
      this perspective. There are other perspectives optimized for other tasks like C++
      development, debugging or result analysis.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Creating &Omnetpp; Projects</title>
    <para>
      In Eclipse, all files are within projects, so first you need a suitable project. The
      project needs to be one designated as an &Omnetpp; Project. (In Eclipse lingo, it
      should have the &Omnetpp; Nature.) The easiest way to create such a project is to
      use a wizard: just choose
      <guimenuitem>File|New|&Omnetpp; Project...</guimenuitem>
      from the menu, specify a project name, and click the
      <guibutton>Finish</guibutton>
      button. If you do not plan to write simple modules, you may unselect the
      <guibutton>C++ Support</guibutton>
      checkbox which will disable all C++ related features on the project.
      <picture file="pictures/Intro-NewProjectWizard.png"> Creating a new &Omnetpp; Project </picture>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Getting Help</title>
    <para>
      You may access the online help system form the
      <guimenuitem>Help | Help Content</guimenuitem>
      menu point. The &Omnetpp; IDE is built on top of the Eclipse ecosystem. If your are
      not familiar with Eclipse we recommend to read the Eclipse and CDT related chapters
      too.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
