<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="tkenv">
  <title>Graphical Runtime Environment</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Features</title>
    <para> Tkenv is a portable graphical windowing user interface. Tkenv supports
      interactive execution of the simulation, tracing and debugging. Tkenv is recommended
      in the development stage of a simulation or for presentation and educational
      purposes, since it allows one to get a detailed picture of the state of simulation
      at any point of execution and to follow what happens inside the network. The most
      important feaures are:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        message flow animation
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        graphical display of statistics (histograms etc.) and output vectors during
        simulation execution
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        separate window for each module's text output
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        scheduled messages can be watched in a window as simulation progresses
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        event-by-event, normal and fast execution
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        labeled breakpoints
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        inspector windows to examine and alter objects and variables in the model
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        simulation can be restarted
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        snapshots (detailed report about the model: objects, variables etc.)
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para> Tkenv makes it possible to view simulation results (output vectors etc.) during
      execution. Results can be displayed as histograms and time-series diagrams. This can
      speed up the process of verifying the correct operation of the simulation program
      and provides a good environment for experimenting with the model during execution.
      When used together with gdb or xxgdb, Tkenv can speed up debugging a lot.</para>
    <para> Tkenv is built with Tcl/Tk, and it work on all platforms where Tcl/Tk has been
      ported to: Unix/X, Windows, Macintosh. You can get more information about Tcl/Tk on
      the Web pages listed in the Reference.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Command-line switches</title>
    <para>A simulation program built with Tkenv accepts the following command line
      switches:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        -h : The program prints a short help message and the networks contained in the
        executable, then exits.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        -f fileName : Specify the name of the configuration file. The default is
        omnetpp.ini. Multiple -f switches can be given; this allows you to partition your
        configuration file. For example, one file can contain your general settings,
        another one most of the module parameters, another one the module parameters you
        change often.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        -l fileName : Load a shared object (.so file on Unix). Multiple -l switches are
        accepted. Your .so files may contain module code etc. By dynamically loading all
        simple module code and compiled network description (_n.o files on Unix) you can
        even eliminate the need to re-link the simulation program after each change in a
        source file. (Shared objects can be created with gcc -shared...)
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        -r : run-number It has the same effect as (but takes priority over) the
        [Tkenv]/default-run= ini file entry.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Tkenv ini file settings</title>
    <para> Tkenv accepts the following settings in the [Tkenv] section of the ini file.
    </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="170" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Entry and default value</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>extra-stack-kb = 48</entry>
            <entry> Specifies the extra amount of stack (in kilobytes) that is reserved
              for each activity() simple module when the simulation is run under Tkenv.
              This value is significantly higher than the similar one for Cmdenv --
              handling GUI events requires a large amount of stack space.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>default-run = 1</entry>
            <entry> Specifies which run Tkenv should set up automatically after startup.
              If there's no default-run= entry or the value is 0, Tkenv will ask which run
              to set up.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>The following configuration entries are of marginal usefulness, because
      corresponding settings are also accessible in the Simulation options dialog in the
      Tkenv GUI, and the GUI settings take precedence. Tkenv stores the settings in the
      .tkenvrc file in the current directory -- the ini file settings are only used if
      there is no .tkenvrc file.</para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="170" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Entry and default value</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>use-mainwindow = yes</entry>
            <entry> Enables/disables writing ev output to the Tkenv main window.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>print-banners = yes</entry>
            <entry> Enables/disables printing banners for each event.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>breakpoints-enabled = yes</entry>
            <entry> Specifies whether the simulation should be stopped at each
              breakpoint() call in the simple modules.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>update-freq-fast = 10</entry>
            <entry> Number of events executed between two display updates when in Fast
              execution mode.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>update-freq-express = 500</entry>
            <entry> Number of events executed between two display updates when in Express
              execution mode.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>animation-delay = 0.3s</entry>
            <entry> Delay between steps when you slow-execute the simulation.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>animation-enabled = yes</entry>
            <entry> Enables/disables message flow animation.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>animation-msgnames = yes</entry>
            <entry> Enables/disables displaying message names during message flow
              animation.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>animation-msgcolors = yes</entry>
            <entry> Enables/disables using different colors for each message kind during
              message flow animation.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>animation-speed = 1.0</entry>
            <entry> Specifies the speed of message flow animation.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>methodcalls-delay =</entry>
            <entry> Sets delay after method call animation.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>show-layouting = true</entry>
            <entry> Show layouting process of network graphics.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <sect2>
      <title>Configuring Tkenv</title>
      <para>In case of nonstandard installation, it may be necessary to set the
        OMNETPP_TKENV_DIR environment variable so that Tkenv can find its parts written in
        Tcl script.</para>
      <para> The default path from where the icons are loaded can be changed with the
        OMNETPP_IMAGE_PATH variable, which is a semicolon-separated list of directories
        and defaults to omnetpp-dir/images;./images.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Using the graphical environment</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>The main window</title>
      <picture file="pictures/Tkenv-main.png" width="300">The main window of the
        Tcl/Tk runtime environment</picture>
      <para>The main window of the simulation environment contains:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          Toolbar: you may access the main functions of the runtime environment.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Status bar: contains several informative values about the current state of the
          simulation.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Timeline: displays the content of the FES on a logarithmic time scale. Double
          clicking on a dot will display the message inspector window.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Object tree: displays all objects currently present in the memory. You may
          double click on nodes to further inspect the given object.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Log Window: contains the output of the simulation.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      The Object tree and the Timeline can be easily switched off on the toolbar if you
      need more space for your log window.
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Inspecting your simulation</title>
      <sect3>
        <title>Networks, Modules</title>
        <picture file="pictures/Tkenv-network.png">Top level network</picture>
        <para>You can start exploring the component hierarchy by browsing the Object
          tree and double clicking on a node or by clicking the Inspect network icon on
          the toolbar. Once you open a node, an inspector window will be opened. Networks
          and compound modules are represented by a graphical inspectors displaying their
          internal structure. Simple modules are represented by object inspectors
          displaying their content as a list. Items in these lists can also be opened.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Future Event Set</title>
        <picture file="pictures/Tkenv-fes.png">The content of the Future Event Set</picture>
        <para>
          You can peek into the Future Event Set by clicking on
          <guimenuitem>Inspect | Scheduled events</guimenuitem>
          . The FES contains all messages already scheduled. Double clicking on any
          message will show the message object's inspector window for further
          investigation.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Output vectors, histograms, queues</title>
        <picture file="pictures/Tkenv-outvector.png">An output vector displayed in a window</picture>
        <para>
          Output vectors have also representation in the model. Double clicking on an
          output vector object displays the content graphically. You may set the display
          properties by clicking on the
          <guibutton>Options...</guibutton>
          button.
        </para>
        <picture file="pictures/Tkenv-histogram.png">A real-time histogram window</picture>
        <para> Histogram inspectors provide a real-time display for the registered
          histograms.</para>
        <note>
          Histograms may not be available right after the simulation start.
        </note>
        <picture file="pictures/Tkenv-queue.png">Peeking into a queue</picture>
        <para> If your simulation contains queue objects, you can peek into them any time.
          All messages currently waiting in the queue are displayed in the queue inspector
          window. Double click on any message to further inspect it.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Browsing your registered components</title>
      <picture file="pictures/Tkenv-registration.png">Display registered functions, classes etc.</picture>
      <para>
        Registered components (NED Types, classes, functions, enums) can be displayed with
        the
        <guimenu>Inspect | Available components</guimenu>
        . If your simulation complains about missing types or classes, it is a good
        practice to check whether everything is loaded and registered correctly. You can
        learn also what configuration entries are currently in effect.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Running and controlling the simulation</title>
      <para>Tkenv has the following modes for running the simulation:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          Step
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Run
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Fast run
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Express run
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The running modes have their corresponding buttons on Tkenv's toolbar.
      </para>
      <para>In Step mode, you can execute the simulation event-by-event.</para>
      <para>In Run mode, the simulation runs with all tracing aids on. Message animation
        is active and inspector windows are updated after each event. Output messages are
        displayed in the main window and module output windows. You can stop the
        simulation with the Stop button on the toolbar. You can fully interact with the
        user interface while the simulation is running: you can open inspectors etc.
      </para>
      <para> In Fast mode, animation is turned off. The inspectors and the message output
        windows are updated after each 10 events (the actual number can be set in
        Options|Simulation options and also in the ini file). Fast mode is several times
        faster than the Run mode; the speedup can get close to 10 (or the configured event
        count).</para>
      <para> In Express mode, the simulation runs at about the same speed as with Cmdenv,
        all tracing disabled. Module output is not recorded in the output windows any
        more. You can interact with the simulation only once in a while, thus the run-time
        overhead of the user interface is minimal. You have to explicitly push the Update
        inspectors button if you want an update.</para>
      <para>
        It is possible to run the simulation until a specified simulation time or event
        number. This is an invaluable tool during debugging sessions. Just select
        <guimenu>Simulate | Run until...</guimenu>
      </para>
      <para>It is also possible run until an event is received in a specified module. Just
      browse for the module and choose <guimenu>Run until next event in this module.</guimenu>
      Simulation will stop once an event arrives to this module.</para>
      <para> Tkenv has a status bar which is regularly updated while the simulation is
        running.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Finding objects</title>
      <picture file="pictures/Tkenv-find.png">Finding a specific object</picture>
      <para>There are times when you don't exactly know the location of the object
        you are looking for. Invoke the "Find/inspect objects" window and search for your
        object. The window allows you to set the start of the search and the type, class
        and name of the object. The results will be presented as a clickable list.</para>
      <note>
        If you are debugging your simulation with a source level debugger and happen to
        know the value of the pointer to your object, you may use the Inspect by pointer
        menu item and insert the pointer value there to display an inspector window for
        the object. Please note that entering an invalid pointer will crash your
        simulation.
      </note>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Logging and module output</title>
      <picture file="pictures/Tkenv-module-out-menu.png">Opening the log of a single module</picture>
      <para>
        Good log output is your best friend during debugging. The main window displays the
        output of the whole simulation, however in some cases you may be interested only
        how a single module is working. Choose
        <guimenuitem>Module output</guimenuitem>
        from the module's context menu.
      </para>
      <picture file="pictures/Tkenv-module-out.png">Module output</picture>
      <para>Module output window displays only messages generated by the selected
        module. You can open several module output window and place them side by side to
        follow the workings of several module at the same time.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Simulation options</title>
      <para>Open <guimenuitem>Options | Simulation options...</guimenuitem>
      to display the runtime environment's preference dialog. You may set global parameters
      for the simulations here. It is possible also to disable various animation primitives
      to speed up the simulation.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>